Dorothea de Schweinitz Papers, 1908-1980
Smith College Archives
Dorothea de Schweinitz Papers
1908-1980
De Schweinitz, Dorothea, 1891-
RG 80. Class of 1912. UUID:8d036122-be57-46c0-b526
2 boxes (1 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Dorothea de Schweinitz was one of the first female regional directors for the National Labor Relations Board, in St. Louis. De Schweinitz worked in employer-labor relations and as an industrial relations specialist for the War Production Board in Washington D.C. Materials include biographical material, correspondence to her parents during her year in Europe after her graduation from Smith College and correspondence between de Schweinitz and her father. Also included are her many publications, both on herself and her family, trade publications on labor and industry, and articles for the Smith Alumnae Quarterly, as well as her memorabilia book from her time at Smith.
Dorothea de Schweinitz was born on September 5, 1891 in Nazareth, Pennsylvania, the third child of Bishop Paul de Schweinitz and Mary Catherine Daniel. De Schweinitz attended the Moravian Parochial School and graduated from Smith College in 1912. Descendant of six generations of ministers, she became a volunteer social worker in Bethlehem after graduation. During her career in vocational and employment guidance work, she also pursued post-graduate studies at the Universities of Wisconsin and Chicago and received her MA in Economics from Columbia University in 1929.
It was in New York City that de Schweinitz became interested in the difficulties of low-skilled laborers through her work as placement secretary at the Central Branch of the Y.W.C.A. de Schweinitz spent twenty years in vocational and employment guidance work, developing a Junior Employment Service in the public schools in Philadelphia and in service for the Pennsylvania State Employment Service, as well as working in the research departments of the Wharton School (Penn.) and the U.S. Employment Service in Washington D.C. In 1937, de Schweinitz was appointed as one of the first of three female regional directors for the National Labor Relations Board, in St. Louis. De Schweinitz spent the next twenty years in employer-labor relations and as an industrial relations specialist for the War Production Board in Washington D.C. beginning in 1942.
After her long and successful career, de Schweinitz gave her time in retirement to another pioneer field, historical preservation, in volunteer work in establishing Georgetown as an historic district. She was also very active in the Washington branch of the Smith College Club. De Schweinitz was awarded a Smith College Medal in 1974.
De Schweinitz received a number of grants to support her studies and publications on employment and labor relations, including one from the Wertheim Committee of Harvard University in 1948.
Until her death at the age of 89 on November 15, 1980, de Schweinitz enjoyed writing and publishing small pieces about her experiences and enjoyed visiting friends in the U.S. and abroad. Her informal writings are uniformly cheerful and articulate and demonstrate, as she would say herself, her diffidence and sociability and sense of responsibility to the community.
The Dorothea de Schweinitz Papers consist of biographical materials, some correspondence to her parents during her year abroad in Europe following her graduation from Smith College (1913-1914), a single correspondence between de Schweinitz and her father during her tenure on the National Labor Relations Board (1939), her many publications, both on herself and her family, trade publications on labor and industry, and for the Smith Alumnae Quarterly, and her memorabilia book from her time at Smith.
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Biographical
II. Correspondence
III. Publications
IV. Memorabilia Book
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
The Dorothea de Schweinitz Papers were donated over a period of time to the Smith College Archives from a variety of sources.
Search Terms
De Schweinitz, Dorothea, 1891-; De Schweinitz, Paul.; Schweinitz family.; Smith College--Students.; Industrial relations--United States--History--20th century--Sources.; Labor--United States--History--20th century--Sources.; Georgetown (Washington, D.C.)--History.; De Schweinitz, Paul.
Additional Information
Related Material
12. Smith College Medal
80. Class of 1912 Records
Dorothea de Schweinitz and Louise de Schweinitz (Darrow) Papers in the Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHY
  - Biographical materials (Box 1)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Correspondence Jan 1913 - Mar 1914 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1939 (Box 1)
- SERIES III. PUBLICATIONS
  - Bibliography (Box 1)
  - Autobiography 1980 (Box 1)
  - Family History 1974 (Box 1)
  - Georgetown 1964, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Industry (Box 1)
- SERIES IV. MEMORABILIA BOOK
  - Memorabilia Book 1908 - 1914 (Box 2)